A Guide to the Papers of the John Powell Foundation, 1945-1986
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of John Powell Foundation, 1945-1986
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8771-g
There are ca. 190 items in this collection.
The papers contain correspondence, programs, rosters, legal documents, clippings and miscellany pertaining to the John Powell Foundation and its goal to encourage and promote performances of Powell's muscial compositions.
This collection of materials was compiled by Florence Richardson Robertson Givens.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection of materials was given to the Library by Suzanne Bunting of Richmond, Virginia, on August 31, 2000.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of items, 1945-1986, n.d., pertaining to the John Powell Foundation and its goal to encourage and promote performances of John Powell's compositions. The correspondence and papers of the Foundation refer to performances and projects of modern composers and other musicians involving the compositions of John Powell; funding and contributions to music projects; and, related topics. Included are correspondence, programs, rosters, legal papers, newspaper clippings, and miscellaneous papers.
Correspondents, 1954-1970, include Edwine Behre, Emma Gray Trigg, Thomas Brockman (1922- ), the Leschetizky Association, Edgar Schenkman, and Steptoe & Johnson, attorneys. The publication of Powell's Sonata Teutonica is among the topics of discussion. Correspondents, 1975-1976, include Roy Hamlin Johnson, Carter Harman of Composers Recordings, Inc., and Vladimir Sokoloff. Topics of discussion include Johnson's proposal for a record of Sonata Teutonica and the lecture-recital of the same. There are a foundation record of expenses and rosters of the Musicians' Club of Richmond. Correspondents, 1977, include Edmund A. Rennolds, Jr., treasurer of the Foundation, Carter Harman of CRI, and John Meredith Langstaff (1920- ). Topics discussed are a discography of works and performances of John Powell, CRI's release of Sonata Teutonica as performed by pianist Roy Hamlin Johnson, and Langstaff's comments on Sonata Teutonica and his request to purchase copies of Five Virginia Folk Songs and Childrens' Songs. From 1977-1981, there is correspondence with Jean M. Bonin, Music Librarian, and Edmund Berkeley, Jr., Curator of Manuscripts, at the University of Virginia concerning the John Powell Collection, which was given to the University Library by the John Powell Foundation. As a pianist often sponsored and supported by the Foundation, Roy Hamlin Johnson (1929- ) is a prominent correspondent throughout the papers. During 1978-1979, the Norfolk Society of Arts corresponds about Florence Richardson Robertson's recital at the Chrysler Museum in April 1978. Other topics of interest include: Roy Hamlin Johnson's proposal to make a redaction of Powell's Symphony; the Oxford University Press' publication of Sonata Teutonica; and, Johnson's progress on his projects and updates on performances. There are also letters from John Diercks (1927- ) concerning Dennis McWater's photograph of Wayman Adams' painting of John Powell. Correspondents, 1980, include Robert W. Kirkpatrick, Fernando Laires (1925- ), and Richard Bales (1915- ), conductor of the National Gallery Orchestra. Topics of interest include progress on Johnson's work on SonataTeutonica; tape recordings of John Powell given to the University of Virginia Library by the John Powell Foundation; the establishment of a John Powell Prize at the University of Maryland; and the premiere of Powell's Symphony in A, as edited by Roy Hamlin Johnson. In 1981, the Foundation makes a grant to the National Gallery of Art for the premiere of Powell's Symphony in A as edited by Johnson. Correspondents, 1981, include Richard Bales, Ernest C. Mead, Jr., and David Edward Collins (1949- ). Mead criticizes Johnson's redaction of Sonata Teutonica and Collins writes about the prospect of recording John Powell's Sonata for Violin and Piano. During 1982-1983, there are letters and papers concerning Roy Hamlin Johnson's projects, such as the printed edition of Sonata Teutonica and work on Sonate Psychologique. Correspondents and topics of interest include Carter Harman of CRI re Sonata Teutonica, Vladimir Sokoloff re a biography of Efrem Zimbalist, and David Edward Collins re sample tapes of a performance of Powell's Sonata. During 1984-1986, there is discussion of Roy Hamlin Johnson's recording techniques involved in Powell's Sonate Psychologique, Powell's Symphony in A 'Virginian' edited by Johnson, Foundation contributions, and the transfer of John Powell's assets in the American Society of Composers, Authors and Publishers to the John Powell Foundation.
The papers of John Powell include "John Powell's Lessons, Summer 1935"; guestbook for "The Leschetizky Club of Richmond, Memorial Recital by John Powell, April 1, 1946, "Rothesay"; a letter, May 25, 1954, from Powell to Maud Karpeles, with an explanation of letter; and, a letter from W. Altvatter Zedtwitz expressing condolences [over the death of John Powell?].
Photographs of John Powell include the photograph of the Wayman Adams' painting of a youthful Powell, ones from his birthday in October 1962, and one from the Virginia Cavalcade. There are also piano lessons and exercises of John Powell.
Contents List
- Brochures of the John Powell Foundation n.d.
- Correspondence and Papers of the John Powell Foundation 1954-1986, n.d., 8 folders
- Memoranda Book for John Powell Foundation 1945-1955, n.d.
- Music Scores: "Sonata in One Movement" for horn and piano, Hornseth Music Company 1978
- Newspaper Articles re John Powell Foundation and the works of John Powell 1954 (1976-1984)
- Papers of John Powell (1935-1963) 1967
- Photographs of John Powell 1962, n.d.
- Piano Exercises of John Powell 1950
- Thesis: "John Powell: Folk Musician" by Sally Twedell Bagley 1970
- Thesis: "John Powell's Piano Suites and Sonatas Noble and Psychologique: A Recording Project" by Wayne Smith 1978
- Thesis: "The Life and Works of John Powell" (draft portions) by Ronald David Ward 1969, 1972, 2 folders